As the sun dips below the horizon
当太阳落下地平线时
its light begins to fade.
它的光芒开始黯淡下来
Night falls and our world descends into darkness.
夜幕降临，我们的世界沉浸在黑暗之中
Today, in our street-lit towns and cities,
今天，在灯火辉煌的小镇和城市
we rarely experience true darkness.
我们几乎体验不到真正的黑暗
But without our eyes to guide us,
但是，没有我们双眼的引导
the world becomes a much more mysterious place.
世界会变得更加神秘
I can't see anything now,
我现在什么也看不见
but strangely I can still sense the presence of the trees
但很奇怪，我依然能感觉到树的存在
enveloping me in the gloom.
它们将我包裹在夜色中
I can't see them, but I know there's something out there.
我看不到它们，但我知道有东西就在那里
And in the same way, as we've explored the cosmos,
同样，当我们探索宇宙时
we've come to realise we can only see
我们已经意识到，对外太空有些什么
the merest hint of what's out there.
我们只能看到仅有的线索
Our best estimate is that more than 99% of the universe
我们最好的估计是，超过99%的宇宙
lies hidden in the dark, invisible to our telescopes
隐藏于黑暗之中，我们的望远镜看不到
and beyond our comprehension.
也超越了我们的理解范围
This film is the story of how we went from thinking
本片故事讲述的就是，我们本以为
we were close to a complete understanding of the universe,
我们已经接近于完全理解宇宙，
to realising we'd seen almost none of it,
后来却意识到，我们所看到只是宇宙的零头
and the extraordinary quest to uncover what's really out there
然后进行了非凡的探索，来揭开在宇宙的黑暗深处
in the dark.
究竟有什么
It's perhaps the most important undertaking in science,
这几乎是最重要的科学事业
because our universe was forged in darkness.
因为我们的宇宙隐藏于黑暗中
And darkness will one day tear it apart.
黑暗总有一天会撕裂它
光明与黑暗
黑暗
For centuries, scientists have used light to build up a seemingly
几个世纪以来，科学家用光构建了一张
comprehensive picture of the universe.
似乎是全方位的宇宙图像
We'd discovered that the Earth was just one planet
我们已经发现，地球只是一颗行星
in orbit around the sun.
它的轨道绕着太阳
And that the sun was itself a star,
而太阳自己是一颗恒星
made of the same stuff as the billions upon billions
组成它的物质与其他无数的星星一样
of stars that light up a vast - perhaps endless - cosmos.
这些星星照亮了浩瀚的，有可能是无尽的，宇宙
天马字幕组出品中文字幕
http://growupsoft.blog.163.com
翻译：旧语新思 马成长  校对：旧语新思 马成长
华中农业大学《欣赏物理学》专用字幕
后期制作：旧语新思 马成长
But there was one niggling problem that had remained unsolved
但是有一个小问题却400多年
for over 400 years, and it was this -
都没有解决，问题是这样的
with so many stars out there,
天空中有这么多星星
why was there any darkness at all?
为什么那里是完全黑暗的？
The story of the dark begins with this simple question.
关于黑暗的故事，就开始于这个简单的问题
And at its heart lies a deep paradox.
其核心部分就是一个深刻的佯谬
In the forest, no matter what direction I point my torch,
在森林中，无论我把手电筒指向哪个方向
the beam will always hit the trunk of a tree.
光柱总是会遇到树干
And just as everywhere I look I see a tree,
正像我无论看哪里都能看到一棵树一样
if the universe is sufficiently large,
如果宇宙足够大
then every line of sight from Earth should end in a star.
那么，从地球看出去每一条视线都会碰到一颗星
The night sky shouldn't be black at all,
夜晚的天空就完全不应该是黑的
it should be ablaze with starlight.
它应该是星光闪耀的
First posed in the 1570s,
这个问题在1570年代第一次提出
this question would become known as Olbers' Paradox.
就是后来众所周知的奥伯斯佯谬
One possible solution was that the Earth was surrounded
一个可能的解释是，地球
by dark stuff that obscured our view of the stars behind.
被不发光物质所包围，使我们看不到后面的星星
But it was soon realised that these dark clouds would absorb
但是不久人们就意识到，这些不发光的云雾会
the light from the stars, heat up and eventually glow
吸收星光的能量，变热，最终
with the same brightness as the stars they obscured.
会发光，与被它们阻挡的星体一样明亮
The paradox was only satisfactorily explained in the 20th century.
这个佯谬在20世纪才有一个满意的解释
The answer - the reason it gets dark at night
答案是 - 夜晚的天空变黑的理由是
is because the universe had a beginning.
宇宙有一个开始
It began with the big bang 13.8 billion years ago, and so
宇宙开始于138亿年前的大爆炸，所以
we only see those stars
我们只会看到这样的星星，
whose light has had time to reach us since then.
它们的光线抵达我们这里需要时间
The sky is dark because light from the most distant stars
天空是黑的，就是因为最远的那些星星的光
hasn't got here yet.
还没有到达我们地球
No mysterious stuff was needed to block out the light.
并没有什么神秘的物质阻碍星光
The dark spaces that starlight had yet to reach were empty,
还在抵达地球的路上的星光，所穿越的黑暗空间就是空的
and cosmologists could sleep easy at night.
宇宙学家在夜晚可以安然入睡了
But before long, we began to see hints that there might be
但是不久之后，我们开始看到一些线索显示
more out there than meets the eye,
除了我们眼睛看到的，太空中还有别的东西
that the shadowy recesses of empty space
也就是说，空荡空间的阴暗角落
might not be so empty after all.
可能终究不是空空荡荡的
The first clues had in fact begun to emerge from the gloom
事实上第一个线索的显现
some 200 years ago,
是在大约200年前
not in the depths of the universe, but in our own back yard.
不是在宇宙的深处，就在我们地球的后院
The invention of the telescope in the 17th century had allowed us
17世纪望远镜的发明，让我们能够
to see the dimmest light from the deepest reaches of the solar system.
看到太阳系最深区域发出来的微弱光线
And in 1781, it had revealed a seventh planet, Uranus,
在1781年，望远镜找到了第七颗行星，天王星
the first to be found since ancient times.
这是古人没有见到过的
But there was something odd about this new planet.
但是，这个新的行星有些奇怪
Astronomers found that as time passed, Uranus's actual position
天文学家发现，随着时间的流逝，天王星的准确位置
was drifting further and further away from the position
越来越偏离引力定律
the laws of gravity predicted it should be at.
所预测的位置
One explanation was that the laws themselves were wrong,
一种解释是，定律本身是错的
but working at the Paris Observatory,
但是，有一个在巴黎天文台工作的人
one man came up with a different solution.
提出了一个不同的解决方案
There was something else out there,
那里还有别的物体
something we couldn't see that was interfering with Uranus's orbit.
就是我们看不到的这个物体，干扰了天王星的轨道
In 1846, the mathematician Urbain Le Verrier
1846年，数学家奥本·勒维耶
was employed at the observatory to calculate the orbits of comets
受雇于天文台来计算彗星
as they wandered through the solar system...
穿越太阳系时的轨道
..and predict when they would light up the night sky.
并预测它们何时点亮夜空
Le Verrier has been described as having an almost pathological
人们这样描述勒维耶，说他有一种几乎病态的
need to impose order on everything and everyone around him,
需求，强迫他身边的每样东西和每个人保持有序
and to have made no allowances for human error or frailty.
不能容忍人们犯错和软弱
When asked what he was like, a colleague remarked,
当被问到他是什么样子时，一个同事说
"I do not know whether Monsieur Le Verrier is actually
我不知道勒维耶先生实际上
"the most detestable man in France,
是否是法国最讨厌的人
"but I am quite certain that he is the most detested."
但我十分肯定他是最讨厌的
But he was undoubtedly a mathematical genius,
但他无疑是一个数学天才
and he was as harsh on himself as he was on others.
他对别人很苛刻，对自己也一样
And because he was a mathematician, he set about finding the object
因为他是一个数学家，他着手寻找
he thought was influencing Uranus not by scouring the skies
他认为正在影响天王星的新天体
with a telescope, but by determining its position through calculation.
不是用望远镜梳理天空，而是通过计算来确定它的位置
These are Le Verrier's original hand-written notes from 1846.
这些就是勒维耶1846年的原始手稿本
This one is called
这本叫做
"Searches of the disturbing body. Second approximation."
“寻找干扰物体. 二阶近似.”
It contains page after page
它包括了一页又一页
of complicated mathematical calculations.
复杂的数学计算
What Le Verrier was attempting was quite different
勒维耶所尝试的做法完全不同于
to what was normally done in astronomy,
天文学中的常规做法
where you know where an object is -
也就是你知道一个天体在哪里 -
say a star or planet or comet - you then use the laws of gravity
比如一颗恒星或行星或彗星 - 然后利用引力定律
to explain its effects on nearby objects.
来解释它对附近天体的影响
Here, he didn't know where his disturbing body was.
而在这里，他不知道他那个干扰天体在哪里
All he had to go by was the effect it had on the orbit of Uranus.
他计算的唯一依靠就是它对天王星的轨道的影响
So he made some starting assumptions about its position, and then
所以他先对干扰天体的位置做出某些初始假定
carried out a calculation to predict the effect it would have on Uranus.
然后进行计算，预测它对天王星产生的影响
He then compared that with what had been observed.
然后与观察结果相比较
When the two didn't match, he went back and adjusted
当二者不匹配时，他再回头调整
his starting assumptions and repeated the calculation.
他最初的假定，然后再重新计算一遍
He did this again and again
他就这样一次又一次重复
until his prediction matched the observation.
直到预测与观察相匹配时才停下来
On the 31st of August, 1846,
1846年8月31号
after three months of painstaking work,
在艰苦工作三个月后
Le Verrier presented his results to the French Academy.
勒维耶把他的结果提交给法国科学院
He announced that his calculations had revealed
他宣布，他的计算显示
what he believed was a new planet,
他相信是一颗新行星
and, crucially, that he had the co-ordinates in the night sky
最关键的是，他给出了夜晚天空的坐标
that showed where it could be found.
用于找到那个新行星
And yet, despite this, he was unable to persuade
然而，尽管如此，他还是不能说服
any French astronomers to search for his planet.
任何法国天文学家去找到他所说的行星
Eventually, Le Verrier sent his calculations
最后，勒维耶把他的计算结果
to Johann Galle at the Berlin Observatory.
寄给了柏林天文台的约翰·加勒
His letter arrived on the 23rd of September,
他的信于9月23日寄到
and the new planet was found the same evening
同一天晚上，他就找到了那颗新行星
within one degree of Le Verrier's predicted location.
它的位置与勒维耶预测的地方差距在一度以内
His calculations were so precise,
他的计算如此精确
it took Galle less than an hour to find it.
以至于加勒找到这颗行星只用了不到一个钟头
Le Verrier and Galle had discovered the planet Neptune.
勒维耶和加勒发现了海王星
A vast ice giant, 17 times heavier than the Earth
一个巨大的冰球，是地球重量的17倍
and nearly 60 times its volume,
体积是地球的60倍
lurking in the shadows some 4 billion kilometres from the sun.
潜伏在离太阳大约40亿千米的阴影中
Neptune had been hard to find
海王星很难被发现
not because there was anything inherently mysterious about it.
不是因为它的内部有什么神秘物质
It's dark simply because it's so far from the sun,
只是因为黑暗，因为它离太阳太远了
there's precious little light to illuminate it.
只有极珍贵的一点阳光照亮它
And outside our solar system,
而在我们的太阳系之外
this lack of illumination is an even bigger problem.
缺乏照明就成了一个更大的问题
And it means even more stuff is hidden in the dark.
这也意味着有更多物质隐藏在黑暗中
Stars are thought to contain just 11% of the atoms in the universe.
人们认为恒星只包含了宇宙中11%的原子
The rest - clouds of gas and dust, planets, dead stars -
剩下的 - 气体云和粉尘，行星，已死亡的恒星 -
we can't see, because they give off hardly any light.
我们都看不见，因为它们几乎不发任何光
The dark spaces between the stars aren't empty at all.
恒星之间的黑暗空间并不完全是空的
In fact, they contain the vast majority
事实上，绝大多数物质
of the stuff that's out there.
都包含在这黑暗空间中
Up until the middle of the 20th century, most astronomers
到20世纪中叶，大多数天文学家相信
believed that, although they couldn't see nearly 90% of it,
虽然有近90%的物质我们看不到
the universe was still, theoretically at least,
整个宇宙依然是完全可见的
entirely visible.
至少理论上是如此
But that was about to change.
但这种观点就要改变了
Welcome to White Sands Missile Range.
欢迎来到白沙导弹试验场
In 1964, NASA scientists fitted an Aerobee rocket
在1964年，NASA的科学家们在一个空蜂火箭
with an X-ray detector...
安装了一台X射线探测器
'..two, one...'
...二，一...
..and blasted it to the edge of space.
将它发射到大气空间边缘
High above the X-ray-absorbing layers of the atmosphere,
在大气层的X射线吸收层之外
the detector spotted something extremely bright
探测器检测到某种极其明显的东西
in the constellation of Cygnus.
位于天鹅座
The young British astronomer Paul Murdin was fascinated by this
年轻的英国天文学家保罗·马丁被这个
mysterious X-ray source, known as Cygnus X-1.
神秘的X射线源迷住了，这个源被命名为 天鹅座X-1
And when he joined the Royal Greenwich Observatory
在他加入格林威治天文台的时候
in the summer of 1971,
也就是1971年夏天
he was given with the perfect opportunity to discover what it was.
他得到了一个绝好的机会去发现它(天鹅座X-1)是什么
It was known that X-rays were produced
大家知道在将气体加热到
when gas was heated to temperatures upwards of a million degrees.
一百万度以上的时候就会产生X射线
DOORBELL CHIMES
【门铃响了】
Hello, Paul!
嗨，保罗！
'But no-one knew for sure what could produce such extreme
但是没有人确切知道，在外太空中
'conditions out in space.'
有什么能导致这种极端条件存在
What was it about X-ray sources that interested you?
关于X射线源是什么让你觉得有趣？
Celestial X-ray sources had just been discovered.
那是天体的X射线源刚刚被发现
They were places in the sky where X-rays came from.
太空中的X射线来自于好几个地方
It's a very energetic radiation,
这是一种能量很高的辐射
it means something really powerful is happening there.
这意味着有某种威力巨大的事情在那里发生
I mean, the X-rays are a flag which the star is waving at you,
我的意思是，X射线是一种标志，表示恒星正在向你招手
saying, "Look at me, look at me, look at me - I'm really interesting."
说，“看看我，看看我，看看我 - 瞧我多有趣.”
But when Paul trained his optical telescope on the source,
但当保罗把他的光学望远镜调整到那个源的时候
all he saw was an ordinary, everyday star,
他看到的只是一颗常见的普通恒星
nowhere near hot enough to produce X-rays.
它附近也没有哪里是热到能产生X射线的
Most stars are in systems where there's two stars,
大多数恒星都构成一个体系，有两颗星的
three stars, even five stars or many more.
三颗星的，甚至有五颗星或者更多的
It's really unusual to have a star like our sun that's on its own.
像太阳这样自己构成一个体系的情况并不常见
I decided therefore that I'd try
因此我决定试试
and look for evidence on the star that I could see, that there
从这可能看见的恒星上寻找证据
was another star nearby and that they were circling one another.
看看附近是否有另一颗星，它们相互绕着对方旋转
By recording its motion night after night, Paul discovered
这样一夜一夜地记录它的运动，保罗发现
the star was orbiting an invisible partner, once every 5.6 days.
这颗星的轨道绕着一颗不可见的伙伴，每5.6天绕一周
What you can calculate, once you know the period of a binary star,
一旦你知道一颗双子星的周期，你就能计算
is the mass of the system and the mass of the component parts of it.
双子星系统和它的各个子星的质量
And so, that was the thing to do next.
所以，这就是接下来要做的事情
And then, maybe within an hour,
然后，可能就在一个钟头内
I knew that the star which I couldn't see
我就知道了这颗我看不见的星
was four solar masses or more.
是太阳质量的四倍或更多
Something that heavy so close to the star he could see
这样重的东西离那颗看得见的恒星这样近
would strip material from its outer layers, the immense
就会从它的外层剥去它的物质，
frictional forces heating the gas to such an extent it produced X-rays.
巨大的摩檫力就会将气体加热到能产生X射线的程度
But physicists only knew of one object that could be that massive
但是物理学家只知道有一种物体会
and yet remain completely invisible.
如此之大却依然完全看不见
It was something that had only ever existed in theory.
这种物体只是在理论上存在着
Paul Murdin had discovered the first black hole.
保罗·马丁发现了第一个黑洞
I was just... I was just elated.
我简直是...我简直是高兴坏了
And I had to get up from my desk and walk about a bit to calm down.
我不得不离开书桌，来回走动一下，以便平静下来
My pulse raced.
我的脉搏也加快了
I knew it was big, but I was also a little bit frightened of it,
我知道这太重大了，所以我也有点害怕出错
so I knew I had to check it very carefully
所以我知道我应该再非常仔细地检查一下
and go through it all again and check what I was doing.
又重新做一遍，检查一下我做的东西
But it was... It was a great hour
但是这是...这真是一个伟大的时刻
and I couldn't really do any serious work for the rest of the day.
那天余下的时间里，我无法平静下来做任何正经事
And I felt... I felt really happy with myself, actually.
我感到...我真为自己感到高兴，真的
Thanks to Paul Murdin,
多亏了保罗·马丁
the universe now had a new and profoundly dark inhabitant.
宇宙现在有了一种极度黑暗的新居民
Black holes are so incredibly dense,
黑洞的密度令人难以置信
their gravity warps the fabric of space and time around them
它们的引力把它们周围的空间和时间弯曲到如此程度，
to such an extent that nothing, not even light, can escape.
以至于无论什么东西，甚至光，都无法逃离它
As you approach a black hole,
当你接近一个黑洞时
an observer watching you from a distance
一个在远处看着你的观察者
will see the light coming from you getting redder and redder.
会看到从你身上发出的光变得越来越红
And you will appear to be moving in slow motion
而且看到你运动的很慢
as the immense gravitational field of the black hole
因为黑洞强大的引力
stretches both space and time.
既扭曲了空间也扭曲了时间
And then, as you pass through the event horizon,
然后，当你穿过了视界之后
the point of no return that marks the edge of a black hole,
也就是没有回头路的那个点，那是黑洞的边缘
you simply disappear, lost from the universe for ever.
你就消失了，从宇宙永远被抹去了
Black holes are objects that would remain dark
无论你把多少光照向它们
no matter how much light you shone on them.
黑洞依然是黑的
Through their effects on other things,
观察它们对其他物体的影响
we've now discovered dozens of black holes in our own galaxy,
我们已经在银河系发现了几十个黑洞
and estimate there must be billions upon billions
而人们估计整个宇宙中
of them throughout the universe.
一定有数十亿个黑洞
Including huge, supermassive black holes
巨大，特大质量的黑洞
millions of times the mass of the sun
质量为太阳的数百万倍
at the heart of nearly every galaxy.
位于几乎每一个星系的心脏部位
As strange as black holes are,
哪怕像黑洞一样奇怪
they were at least something we'd expected to find.
毕竟是我们期望能够找到的东西
We had theories that predicted their existence
我们的理论已经预测到它们的存在
and described their properties.
并描述了它们的性质
But since the 1930s,
但是自20世纪30年代以来
astronomers had seen disturbing hints of something much stranger.
天文学家已经看到了令人不安的线索，提示有比黑洞更奇怪的东西
Stuff that was both completely invisible and completely unexpected.
这种物质是完全不可见的，也完全在预料之外
FAINT WHISPERING
『低语声』
As a child, Vera Rubin spent hours awake at night
还是一个孩子的时候，薇拉·鲁宾经常数小时深夜醒来
staring out of the window above her bed,
看着她床头的窗户外面
gazing at the stars as they moved across the sky.
凝望着星星划过天空
Then, in her 30s and a mother herself,
后来，在她30多岁的时候已是为人之母
she decided to realise her childhood dream
她决定去实现她的童年梦想
and embark on a career as an astronomer.
把天文学家作为自己的职业
FAINT WHISPERING
『低语声』
In the mid 1960s, the hottest topic in astronomy was quasars.
在20世纪六十年代，天文学中最热门的课题就是类星体
But the field was extremely crowded
但是因为野外嘈杂
and because the biggest telescopes that were needed to study them
研究类星体所必须的最大的望远镜
were often in the remotest parts of the world,
经常在地球最偏远的地方
working on quasars meant a lot of time spent away from home.
研究类星体就意味着要在离家很远的地方工作很长时间
So Vera needed to find a research topic
所以薇拉必须找到一个研究课题
that was more compatible with being a working mum,
不影响她做上班族妈妈
and a smaller field where she could really make her mark.
同时，这个领域还必须比较小，以便她能够真正达到目的
So she began a project measuring the way stars move within galaxies
就这样，她开始一个项目，测量恒星在星系中的移动方式
like our own Milky Way.
这些星系就像我们自己的银河系
- Whoa! - HE LAUGHS
— 哇!『— 他笑了』
Everything in a galaxy is on the move and rotating.
星系中的所有物体都在移动和旋转
In one minute, the Earth travels
一分钟内，地球会绕太阳
nearly 2,000 kilometres around the sun.
旅行近2000千米
But in that same time, the sun and the entire solar system
而在同样的时间内，太阳和整个太阳系
travel 12,000 kilometres around the centre of the Milky Way galaxy.
会绕着银河系中心旅行1万2000千米
Ah!
哇
I'm not liking this!
我可不喜欢这样！
If you think this is spinning fast, think about this.
如果你认为这转得快，那么考虑一下这个
The Earth is travelling around the sun at 108,000 kilometres an hour.
地球绕太阳飞行速度是每小时10万8000千米
Ha! And the sun and the entire solar system
哈！太阳和整个太阳系
are travelling at 720,000 kilometres an hour
绕银河系中心飞行的速度是
around the centre of the galaxy.
每小时72万千米
HE LAUGHS
『他笑了』
Can we stop it now?
我现在可以停下来了吗？
That's done me in, that really has.
这可要了我的命，真的
Thanks very much.
太感谢了
But when Vera Rubin measured the speed of stars
但是当薇拉·鲁宾测量仙女座星系里
orbiting the centre of the Andromeda Galaxy,
绕星系中心轨道运行的恒星速度时
she found something deeply puzzling.
她发现了令人深感困惑的事情
If I plot a graph of the speed
如果我画一幅图，纵轴表示
at which planets in our solar system orbit the sun
我们太阳系中的行星的速度
against their distance from the sun,
横轴表示它们到太阳的距离
I find that the closest planet, Mercury, orbits the fastest.
我发现，离太阳最近的行星，水星，轨道速度最快
It's then followed by Venus, Earth, Mars and so on.
然后是金星，地球，火星，等等
The further out you go...
离太阳越远
the slower the orbit.
轨道速度越慢
In fact, Neptune moves so slowly relative to the other planets
事实上，海王星与其他行星比起来移动的很慢
and has so far to go in orbit around the sun,
它的轨道离太阳如此之远
that it's only completed one full circuit
以至于从我们在167年前发现它以来
since it was discovered 167 years ago.
只绕轨道运行了一整圈
Now, if I plot the same graph again of speed against distance,
现在，如果我再画一张同样的速度-距离图
but this time, the speed
但是这一次，速度是
at which the stars orbit the centre of a galaxy
恒星绕星系中心轨道运行的速度
against their distance from the centre,
距离则是恒星到星系中心的距离
I'd expect to see for the outer stars,
我希望看到，对于更外面的恒星
that the speed drops off with distance, as it did for the planets.
速度随着距离而下降，就像太阳系的行星一样
But when Vera Rubin plotted her data,
但是当薇拉·鲁宾做出她的数据图形时
she found that the further out you went,
她发现你越往外面更远
the speed of the stars didn't drop off,
恒星的速度并不是越慢下来
it remained roughly the same.
而是大致维持不变
The planets move more slowly the further out they are
行星月往外面更远运动的越慢
because the further you go,
因为当你走得越远
the weaker the sun's gravitational field becomes.
太阳的引力场就会变得越微弱
So anything moving too fast would simply fly off into outer space.
所以，任何移动得太快的物体就会干脆飞向外太空
But Vera Rubin's result for galaxies
但是薇拉·鲁宾从星系得到的结果
suggested there must be an extra source of gravity
暗示一定有一个额外的引力源
holding all those fast-moving stars in their orbits.
让这些快速移动的星体保持在它们的轨道上
This extra gravity was needed
这种额外的引力是必须的
because when astronomers added up the gravitational pull
因为天文学家把包括他们能想到的
of all the dark things they thought might be lurking in the galaxy,
所有可能潜伏在星系中的黑暗物质
planets, clouds of dust, even black holes,
行星，尘埃云，甚至黑洞的引力都加起来
it always came out about ten times less
要导致星体的速度
than that needed to account for
像薇拉·鲁宾所测得的那样
the stellar speeds Vera Rubin had measured.
其引力依然少大约10倍
There were two possible explanations.
有两个可能的解释
Either Einstein's theory of gravity was wrong,
要么爱因斯坦的引力理论是错的
or galaxies were full of a completely new kind of stuff.
要么星系被一种全新的物质所充满
Something that wasn't made of atoms,
这种东西不是由原子构成
was completely invisible and very heavy.
完全不可见，而且非常重
A new form of dark matter.
这是一种新的黑暗物质形式
Something astronomers named... dark matter.
天文学家命名这种东西为... 暗物质
Unsurprisingly, rather than accept
毫不奇怪，比起接受
that galaxies were full of some mysterious unseen stuff,
星系中充满了某种神秘的看不见的物质
some physicists once again thought tweaking the laws of gravity
一些物理学家再次想到，修改引力定律
might be the simplest solution.
可能是最简单的解决方案
That was until astronomers captured an astonishing image.
直到天文学家捕获了一副惊人的画面
For me, this is one of the most
对我而言，这是现代天文学中
amazing pictures in modern astronomy.
最令我吃惊的画面之一
It's an image of a cluster of galaxies called the Bullet Cluster.
这是一张星系簇团的照片，名叫“子弹星系团”
It gets its name from this bullet-shaped cloud of gas,
它的这个名称来源于这种子弹形状的气体云，
which is actually a shockwave caused by the collision
它实际上是由碰撞引起的冲击波
not of just clouds of gas or stars or even whole galaxies,
不只是气体云或恒星，甚至也不是整个星系
but clusters of galaxies coming together
而是星系团簇相遇后
and passing through each other at 10-million kilometres an hour.
相互穿过，速度达每小时1000万千米
It almost gives me vertigo trying to imagine the immensity of the scale.
当我想到这碰撞规模之巨大时，都感到一阵眩晕
But it's not the magnitude of the collision
但是碰撞规模的巨大
that makes this image so important.
并不会使这幅照片如此重要
It's what it did to the clusters' constituent parts.
是碰撞对簇团的各部分产生的后果使它变得重要
As the clusters came together,
当这些星系团相遇时
the stars and planets in the galaxies
星系中的恒星和行星
pretty much passed through each other
大部分会相互穿过
because although they're big, the distances between them are so vast
因为虽然它们很大，但它们之间的距离也很大
that the chances of any two stars colliding is actually very small.
两颗恒星相撞的机会事实上很小
But that doesn't apply to the dust and gas
但是那些尘埃和气体就不是这样了
that makes up 90% by mass of all the stuff we can see in a galaxy.
它们的质量占我们能看见的星系总物质的90%
When these collide, they create a huge, hot cloud -
当它们碰撞时，它们就产生了巨大的热云
these two pink regions in the centre of the image.
也就是位于照片中心的两块粉红色区域
But if most of the mass is trapped here in the clouds,
但是，如果大多数质量都陷于云的这里，
then you'd expect most of the gravity to be centred there, too.
那么你一定希望大多数引力也会以那里为中心
But that's not what you see.
但是你所看到的并不是这样
These outer blue regions show where light has been bent round
这些更外面的蓝色区域表明光在这里被弯曲
as gravity warps the fabric of space itself.
因为引力把空间自身的构造扭曲了
That means most of the gravity is centred out here,
这就意味着大多数引力的中心在这里
rather than in the middle.
而不是在正中间
The simplest way to explain this
对此，最简单的解释是
is that it wasn't just stars and planets
在星系团相互撞击的时候
that passed through as the clusters collided,
并不只有恒星和行星相互穿过
something else did, too.
还有其他物质穿过
Something massive, yet invisible.
这种物质巨大，但不可见
This image is the best evidence we have yet
这幅图片是我们未曾有过的
for the existence of dark matter.
证明暗物质存在的最好证据
It's now generally accepted that dark matter is real,
现在人们普遍接受了暗物质是真实的观点
which means there's far more stuff in the universe than we'd thought.
这意味着宇宙中的物质比我们曾经设想过的多很多
In fact, there's four times
事实上，暗物质的数量
as much dark matter as there is normal matter.
是正常物质的四倍之多
And so vast swathes of the universe are not just unseen,
宇宙中如此之多的东西，不光是看不见
they're fundamentally unseeable.
它们从本质上来说就是不可见的
The reason dark matter is so elusive
暗物质如此难以捉摸的原因是
is because it doesn't reflect light and it doesn't emit light.
它既不反射光也不发射光
So we can't see it.
所以我们就看不见它
And worse than that, what gives normal matter its solidity
还有比这更糟糕的，正常的物质之所以具有固体性
is the electromagnetic force.
是因为有电磁力
And dark matter particles don't feel that force,
而暗物质粒子感受不到这种力
so they just pass straight through matter.
所以它们就会直接穿过其它物质
The only hope we have is if they hit an atomic nucleus head-on.
我们能有的唯一希望就是它们是否能和原子核迎头相撞
And even if they do, that's really hard to detect.
而且即使它们撞上了，我们也极难探测到这种撞击
And so the hunt for dark matter
所以，对暗物质的搜寻
has turned from the incredibly large to the unimaginably small.
已经从极大的方面转到极小的方面
From scouring the skies with telescopes
从用望远镜梳理天空
to detectors buried deep underground.
转到把探测器深埋于地下
When it comes to the search for dark matter,
在寻找暗物质的时候
the place I'm going to is pretty much the centre of the universe.
我正在前往的地方，几乎相当于宇宙的中心
The Gran Sasso National Laboratory
这就是格兰萨索国家实验室
lies beneath almost a kilometre and a half of solid rock.
位于几乎1500米岩石覆盖的地下
And can only be reached through a tunnel
要到达那里，只能通过一条
cut deep into the Italian Apennines.
深入到意大利亚平宁山脉的隧道
The reason you'd build a laboratory underneath a mountain
之所以把实验室建在一座山里面
is because our planet is constantly being bombarded by cosmic rays.
是因为地球总是持续地受到宇宙射线的轰击
These collide with the upper atmosphere,
它们与外层大气发生碰撞
creating a cascade of particles
产生级联放大的粒子流
that shower down onto the surface of the Earth.
倾泻到地球表面
The rock above me effectively forms a 1400-metre-thick roof
我头顶上的岩石形成了一个有效的1400米厚的顶层
that absorbs most of these particles,
吸收掉绝大部分这些粒子
shielding and protecting the equipment below.
屏蔽和保护下面的设备
But crucially for dark-matter hunters,
但是，对暗物质搜寻者而言，最关键的是
it passes straight through normal matter,
暗物质直接穿过正常物质
straight through the rock,
直接穿过岩石
and the hope is, into their detectors.
并希望它进入到他们的探测器
Oh!
哇！
It looks like a Bond villain's evil lair.
这看起来像邦德的邪恶巢穴
Gran Sasso is the world's largest underground laboratory.
格兰萨索是世界上最大的地下实验室
And for the last ten years,
在过去十年里
it's been home to dark matter scientists like Dr Chamkaur Ghag,
它就是暗物质科学家的家，比如Chamkaur Ghag博士
who works on DarkSide-50,
他在DarkSide-50探测器上工作
one of five dark matter experiments based here.
其上进行的是五个暗物质实验之一
- So hairnet.  - Hairnet.
- 这是发网.  - 发网.
Or head net, in my case.
或者叫头网, 我头发少.
- Milligram levels of dust can destroy the experiment. - Right.
毫克水平的粉尘就能毁坏实验. - 好的
That looks very impressive.
看起来非常让人印象深刻
- Yep. - Very sci-fi.
- 是哦. - 相当科幻啊.
So tell me, how does the experiment work?
那么给我讲讲，这个实验怎样运转啊？
Well, the entire experiment is configured like a Russian doll,
好的，整个实验搭建起来就像一个俄罗斯玩偶
where the first outer layer is the mountain itself,
最外面的一层就是这座高山自身
protecting the experiment from radiation from space.
用来保护实验免受太空辐射的影响
Then we have this tank that we're standing in.
然后就是这个水槽，就是我们站着的地方
And this tank is going to be flooded full of water.
这个水槽会被水完全淹没
What, the whole cylinder?
什么，整个缸都淹？
Absolutely. This is all completely filled to the brim.
绝对正确。全部放满，直到这个边沿
About 750 cubic metres of water will fill this thing
大约有750立方米的水会放到这里面
to stop radiation coming from the laboratory and the rock around us.
就是要阻止来自实验室和我们周围的岩石的辐射
That's protecting this huge metal sphere right here,
这保护着这个巨大的金属球，就是这，
which is the final layer of protection
它是最后一层保护层
before we get to DarkSide itself, which is inside there right now.
然后就是DarkSide装置本身了，就在这里面
That's the detector, that's the heart of the experiment.
这就是探测器，这个实验的心脏
That's the thing that will be detecting dark matter.
就是这个东西，将会探测暗物质
- You haven't got a light switch up there. - No.
- 这里没有一个灯的开关咧.   - 嗯，没有.
I'm going to get up there and have a look.
我要爬到那里看一看
DarkSide-50 is designed to detect
DarkSide-50是设计用来探测
a new class of fundamental particles
一类新的基本粒子的
called weakly interacting massive particles.
叫做大质量弱相互作用粒子（WIMP）
Predicted by theory, it's thought that these WIMPs
根据理论预测，人们认为这些WIMP
might be the stuff of which dark matter is made.
可能就是组成暗物质的材料
So that metal sphere in the centre, that's DarkSide?
那么在中间的那个金属球，那就是DarkSide吗？
That's right. That's a detector full of 150kg of liquid argon.
对. 这是一个探测器，装满了150千克的液态氩
Dark matter particles should be
暗物质粒子应该
streaming through the detector all the time,
一直都在流过这个探测器
but most of them just go straight through
但是绝大多数都只是直接穿过
because they're very weakly interacting particles.
因为它们是非常弱的相互作用粒子
If we're lucky, one will collide with the nucleus of an argon atom,
如果我们运气好，就会遇到一个粒子撞上某个氩原子的核
producing flashes of light that the detector will pick up.
就会发生闪光，探测器就会捕捉到
DarkSide is yet to begin its search,
DarkSide还没有开始搜索
but elsewhere in the laboratory's labyrinth of tunnels,
但是在实验室隧道迷宫的其他地方
they're already seeing tantalising hints.
他们已经看到了诱人的提示
This is the XENON100 experiment that's already running
这是已经开始运行的XENON100实验
and taking data and has been for a while.
正在获取数据，已经有一段时间了
It's the most sensitive dark matter detector in the world right now.
它是当今世界最敏感的暗物质探测器
And this is a live feed of dark matter data coming in right now.
这是一个暗物质数据获取的实况
So, what exactly... What sort of signal or shape are you looking for?
那么，确切地说... 你们正在寻找的是哪种信号或形状?
Well, what we're looking for is an initial flash of light
哦，我们正在寻找一种初始闪光
which will be a very sharp peak like this,
那会是一种非常尖的尖峰，就像这样，
followed by a much larger peak like that one,
然后是一个更大的峰，像那个一样，
which is light being generated in a gas layer
它就是在液态氙顶部的
on top of the liquid xenon.
气体层生成的光
Oh. That could be a good one as well, actually.
哦. 事实上, 这可能也是一个不错的信号
There you go.
这边请.
So any one of those events, those spikes,
那么那些事件，那些峰值的任何一个
could be a dark matter particle?
都可能是一个暗物质粒子？
That's right. Any one of these events
正是. 任何一个这样的事件
could be the signature of dark matter
都有可能是在XENON100中
interacting in XENON100.
发生相互作用的暗物质
It's just we won't know for sure until the data's been analysed.
只是在分析这些数据之前，我们还不能确定
Because it's so sensitive,
因为它太敏感了
the overwhelming majority of the spikes
绝大多数这些峰值
are due to radiation emitted by the metal
都是因为组成探测器本身的
that makes up the detector itself.
金属所发出来的辐射
But the hope is experiments like this
但是我们希望像这样的实验
will definitively detect dark matter particles
在未来十年内一定能
within the next ten years.
探测到暗物质粒子
Today, we think that dark matter not only exists,
今天，我们认为暗物质不光存在，
but that it is a vital part of our universe,
而且是我们宇宙至关重要的一部分
because without it, the world that we can see wouldn't exist
因为没有它，我们能看到的世界将不会存在
and that's because dark matter not only holds galaxies together,
因为暗物质不仅把星系维持在一起
it's dark matter that brought the clouds of gas together
而且正是它把尘埃云集合到一起
to form the galaxies in which stars could ignite in the first place.
形成星系，从而使恒星能够在其中点火燃烧起来
Dark matter has gone from being a curious quirk
暗物质最初只是一种奇怪的巧合
of the way stars move around the fringes of galaxies
使恒星绕星系边缘按特定方式运动
to the reason there are stars and galaxies at all.
现在它成了恒星和星系存在的理由
But in the late 1990s, scientists attempting
但是在20世纪90年代末期，在科学家试图
to measure exactly how much dark matter there was
到底有多少暗物质的时候
made an astonishing discovery.
又有了一个令人惊讶的发现
There was something even more mysterious
还有某种更神秘的东西
and even more elusive out there.
更难以捉摸的东西存在于太空
And to understand what that is,
为了搞清楚那到底是什么
you have to go back to the very beginning of everything.
你要回到万物诞生之初
The universe began with a gigantic fireball.
宇宙开始于一个巨大的火球
13.8 billion years ago, the universe was born.
138亿年前，宇宙诞生了
In the so-called big bang,
在这被称为大爆炸的时候
everything was created simultaneously.
万物同时被创造出来
See that great flash of light?
看到了这巨大的闪光吗？
That's all the pieces of the atoms joining together to make a gas.
那就是所有原子碎片正结合在一起形成气团
And now the gas is getting lumpy.
现在气团在形成块状物体
It's making the giant galaxies of stars.
然后形成巨大的恒星星系
The expansion of the universe that we now see
我们现在所看到的宇宙的膨胀
is just a remnant of the initial violent explosion.
只是最初猛烈的爆炸的遗迹
The big bang means that in the past,
大爆炸意味着，在过去
the universe was much smaller than it is today.
宇宙比它今天的样子要小很多
And it's been getting bigger ever since.
从那时到现在，它正在变得更大
According to the big bang theory,
根据大爆炸理论
the universe has been expanding for the past 13.8 billion years.
宇宙在过去138亿年一直在膨胀
And for most of that time,
在大多数时间里
you'd expect the expansion to be slowing down
你希望这种膨胀会慢下来
due to the combined gravitational attraction
因为宇宙中所有质量的
of all the mass in the universe
万有引力组合起来
trying to pull it back together again.
会试图把物质拉回到一起
Now, here's the clever bit,
现在，这里有一个好点子
Cosmologists realised that by measuring
宇宙学家认识到通过测量
how much the expansion was slowing,
膨胀慢下来的速度
they could calculate how much stuff was out there.
他们就能计算太空中有多少物质
In a sense, it would allow them to weigh the entire universe.
从某种意义上来说，这会让他们能称量整个宇宙的重量
But in order to measure how the universe is expanding,
但是，为了测量宇宙是如何膨胀的
you need a reliable way to measure distances in space.
你需要一种可靠的方法来测量空间的距离
Something of known brightness, astronomers call a standard candle.
对于已知亮度的东西，天文学家称其为标准蜡烛
The flame in this lantern produces a fixed amount of light.
这个灯笼里面的火焰产生的光量是固定的
It has a specific brightness that I can measure here on the ground.
它具有特定的亮度，我可以在此地测量它
But if I let the lantern go, it'll drift away
但是当我放开灯笼，它就会飘走
and the light will appear to get dimmer and dimmer
随着它飘得越来越远
the further away it gets.
它的光也会显得越来越暗
Because I know how bright it really is,
因为我知道它真正的亮度是多少
by comparing that with how bright it appears,
把它显示的亮度与真正的亮度相比较
I can calculate how far away it is.
我就能计算出它在多远的地方
And because every lantern's the same,
因为每一个灯笼的实际亮度都是一样的
I can use the brightness to calculate the distance
我就能通过亮度来计算
to any lantern I see in the sky.
我在天空中看到的任何灯笼的距离
The astronomical equivalent of a Chinese lantern
天文学中与中国灯笼等价的是
is a particular species of exploding star called a Type 1a supernova.
一种特殊的爆发星，叫做1a型超新星
These stars always explode when they reach the same critical mass
这些恒星总是在它们到达相同的临界质量的时候爆炸
and so always explode with the same brightness.
所以总是发出同样的亮度
So by measuring how bright they appear,
所以通过测量它们看起来有多亮
we can tell how far they are from the Earth.
我们就能告诉你它们离地球有多远
As well as telling us how far away they are,
除了告诉我们它们有多远
the light reaching us from distant supernovae tells us something else.
从超新星到达地球的光还能告诉我们其他一些情况
As it travels across the cosmos, light gets stretched
当光穿过宇宙时，它会伸展
because the space it's travelling through is expanding.
因为光穿过的空间正在膨胀
And as its wavelength increases, the light gets redder and redder.
随着它的波长的增加，光变得原来越红
And this red shift tells us how fast the universe was expanding
这种红移告诉我们在光离开它的源的时候，
when the light left its source, when the star exploded.
当新星爆炸的时候，宇宙膨胀有多快
But when scientists analysed light from the more distant supernovae
但是当科学家分析从更远处传来的光的时候
they found something strange.
他们发现了奇怪的情况
It was less stretched than expected.
光的伸展量比预期的要小
It meant that, in the past,
这就意味着，在过去
the universe was expanding more slowly than it is today.
宇宙的膨胀要比现在更慢
In other words, the expansion of the universe wasn't slowing down at all,
换句话说，宇宙的膨胀完全不是在变慢
it was speeding up.
而是越来越快
The only way the universe's expansion could be accelerating...
能够让宇宙加速膨胀的唯一方式...
..was if there was a mysterious new force pushing it apart.
..就是，是否有一种神秘的新力在把它分离
And just as with dark matter, physicists thought the key
就像在面对暗物质时一样，物理学家认为理解
to understanding this new force
这种新的力之关键
might lie at the smallest possible scales...
可能隐藏于最小可能的尺度中...
..because quantum physics appeared to provide a ready-made explanation.
..因为量子物理学似乎提供了一种已有的解释
According to quantum field theory, empty space is anything but empty.
根据量子场论，真空包含万物，而不是空的
Particles are constantly appearing and disappearing,
粒子不断地出现和消失
created out of energy borrowed from the vacuum itself.
创造出从真空本身借来的能量
The hope was that this theoretical vacuum energy
物理学家期望这种理论上的真空能量
might be the very thing that was pushing the universe apart.
可能就是推动宇宙分离的东西
And the theory allows me to calculate the energy density
这个理论使我们能计算真空的
of the vacuum, that's the amount of energy you'd expect to find
能量密度，也就是在一个给定的体积内你希望
in a given volume.
找到的能量数量
And so if I take the energy of the vacuum
这样的话，如果我从真空获得的能量
to be a sum over J of half h-bar omega J,
就是对j求和1/2乘h-bar乘欧米茄j
and if I take the cut-off energy
并且如果我取截断能量
to be of the order of 10 tera electronvolts
为10万亿电子伏特的量级
which is just above the known physics
这个量级恰好高于大型强子对撞机上
at the Large Hadron Collider, then the formula for the vacuum...
已知的物理学，那么真空的公式...
'All they needed to do was check the energy density the theory predicted
他们需要做的只是核对一下理论所预测的能量密度
'matched that needed to drive the universe's acceleration
匹配驱动宇宙加速膨胀所需要的能量密度
'and the mysterious force would be explained.'
这样这种神秘的力就能得到解释了
HE MUTTERS EQUATIONS
『他念叨着方程』
So that would give me a value for the energy density
这样，就给了我一个真空的真空的能量密度值
of the vacuum of 10 to the 35 kilograms per cubic metre.
为每立方米10的35次方千克
The trouble is, the value observed by astronomers
麻烦的是，天文学家所观测到的值
is 10 to the minus 27 kilograms per cubic metre.
是10的-27次方千克每立方米
That means the theoretical number and the experimental number
这意味着，理论上的数与实验上的数据
are out by a factor of 10 to the power 62.
相差10的62次方倍
That's one followed by 62 zeros.
也就是1的后面跟62个零
To give you a sense of the scale of the error,
为了让你对这种错误的程度有些感觉
there've been only 10 to the 17 seconds
这就相当于说，从大爆炸到现在只过了
since the big bang and the diameter of the entire visible universe
10到17秒，整个可视宇宙的直径
is 10 to the 27 metres...
只有10到27米...
So it's a pretty big error.
所以这是一个相当大的错误
And that meant that whatever was actually pushing the universe apart,
这意味着无论是什么在实际推动宇宙分离
it was something completely new.
它都是某种全新的东西
The truth is, we know very little about what's causing
真相是，对是什么导致宇宙膨胀的加速
the expansion of the universe to accelerate,
我们知道的很少很少
but we do have a name for it - dark energy.
但是我们却给它取了一个名字 - 暗能量
And we know that for it to have the effect that it does,
而且我们知道，为了让它能够起发挥应有的效应
there must be an awful lot of it about.
周围必须存在极多的暗能量
Einstein's famous equation E=mc^2
爱因斯坦的著名公式E=mc^2
says that energy and matter are different forms of the same thing.
说能量与物质是同一种东西的不同形式
And the equivalent mass of dark energy dwarfs that
暗能量的等价质量使宇宙中
of everything else in the universe.
其他所有东西的质量相形见绌
And it means that, today,
这就意味着，在今天，
normal matter makes up just 4% of the cosmos.
正常的物质只占宇宙的4%
23% of it is elusive dark matter.
宇宙的23%是难以捉摸的暗物质
And a colossal 73% of the universe
而宇宙庞大的73%
consists of mysterious dark energy.
都由神秘的暗能量组成
Just think about it for a moment.
试想一下
100 billion galaxies,
1千亿个星系
each one containing more than 100 billion stars,
每个星系包含超过1千亿的恒星
home in turn to billions upon billions of planets and moons.
这些恒星反过来又是数不清的行星和卫星的家园
All of that is mere flotsam adrift on a vast and unfathomable ocean.
所有这些只是漂泊在巨大的深不可测的海洋中的废料
Dark matter we can't see and dark energy we can barely comprehend.
暗物质我们看不见，暗能量我们几乎不能理解
And the very nature of dark energy means the universe is getting
暗能量的本质意味着宇宙正变得
more unknowable all the time.
更加不可知了
As space expands and distances become bigger,
随着空间的膨胀，间距变得更大
most forces get weaker, because you have the same amount of mass
大多数作用力变得更弱了，因为你有同样的质量或电荷
or electric charge, only now everything's further apart.
只是现在每样物质都分开得更远了
But dark energy behaves completely differently.
但是暗能量的行为完全不同
As the universe has expanded, the stronger it's become.
随着宇宙的膨胀，它变得更强了
The more space there is, the more dark energy there is
空间越多，暗能量就越多
and so the faster the universe expands,
这样宇宙就膨胀得越快
creating ever more space and ever more dark energy.
同时就会创造更多的空间和更多的暗能量
And that has a profound consequence.
这就会有一个深远的后果
Just as dark matter pulled the galaxies together
就像暗物质把星系拉在一起
to create the cosmos as we know it...
创造了我们已知的宇宙一样...
..so dark energy will tear the universe apart.
..暗能量则会把宇宙撕开
In the future, as space gets bigger,
在未来，随着空间膨胀越来越大
dark energy will become ever more dominant.
暗能量将会变得更加站主导地位
And so it will ultimately shape the universe's destiny.
就这样，暗能量最终会塑造宇宙的命运
And if it continues to increase as it appears to be doing today,
如果暗能量继续增加，就像现在这样，
then it will push the galaxies further and further apart
那么，它就会把星系推得越来越远
until, eventually, they slip out of view,
直到，最终，它们离开我们的视野
creating a cosmos that will become ever more dark
这样的宇宙将会变得更加黑暗
and ever more desolate.
也更加孤寂
The ultimate goal of modern cosmology is to understand
现代宇宙学的终极目标
dark energy and the fate of the universe,
就是理解暗能量和宇宙的命运，
and to witness how dark matter brought everything together
并见证暗物质最初是如何
in the first place.
把万物聚集在一起的
And so to shed light on both the beginning and end of the universe,
所以，为了完全理解宇宙的开始和结局
cosmologists have embarked on a quest of epic proportions -
宇宙学家们开始着手构建宏伟巨作 -
to map everywhere in space over the entire lifespan of the cosmos...
把宇宙的整个生命周期中空间的每一处都绘制出来...
..starting with the darkest period in its past,
..从宇宙过去的最黑暗时期开始，
an era that began as the afterglow of the big bang faded away.
那是大爆炸消褪的晚霞余辉出现的年代
We talk about the ages of the universe in the same way
我们谈论起宇宙的寿命，就像
that we talk about the stages in our own lives, from its birth,
在谈论我们自己的生命各阶段一样，从它的诞生，
through childhood, adolescence, adulthood and even death.
经过童年，青春期，成年直到死亡.
So mapping the universe is really about
所以绘制宇宙图像实际上就是
filling in the photo album of its life.
填补宇宙生命的相册
Here's a picture of me from 20 years ago with my children.
这里是我的一张相片，那是20年前和我的孩子们在一起.
I know it because I have a lot more hair there.
我知道那是啥时候，因为我那时头发更多.
And here's a picture of me in my early 20s on graduation.
而这张我的照片是在我20多年前大学毕业的时候
And here's one of me as a teenager.
这张里面的我还是一个青少年
In the same way, by looking out into space,
用同样的方式，通过观察太空
we have good images of the universe
我们有很好的宇宙图像
all the way back to its teenage years,
直到宇宙的青少年时期
when large galaxies first formed.
那时候星系刚开始形成
But before that, we have nothing but a single image -
但在此之前的，我们只有唯一一张图片
a picture of the universe when it was just 400,000 years old,
是宇宙只有40万年的时候的图片
the cosmic microwave background - the afterglow of the big bang.
就是宇宙微波背景 - 那就是大爆炸的晚霞余晖
It's as though, in the photo album of my life,
这就好像是，在我一生的相册中,
I have nothing before this picture of me aged 16,
这张我16岁时候的照片，再往前就啥都没有了
apart from this one of me and my parents in Iraq
除了这张我和我父母在伊拉克的照片，
when I was just a few months old.
那时候我只有几个月大
This gap in the childhood of the universe,
这种宇宙童年时期的空白
the period between its earliest moments, through the birth
也就是从宇宙最早时期，到第一批
of the first stars to the formation of large galaxies
恒星的诞生，形成大星系
is a time known as the dark ages of the universe.
这段时期就是宇宙的黑暗时代
The universe's dark ages lasted for around a billion years
宇宙的黑暗时代持续了大约十亿年
and they get their name because there were precious few stars
得到这样的名称，是因为那个年代只有极珍贵的很少的
to illuminate them.
恒星点缀着宇宙
So to fill in those pages in the cosmic photo album, we'd need
所以，为了填补宇宙相册的那些空白页面，我们需要
something capable of seeing where there was next to no light.
一种东西能够看到几乎没有光的地方
During the Second World War, Bernard Lovell had developed a machine
在二次大战时期，伯纳德·洛弗尔开发了一种设备
that could see in the dark.
能够看透黑暗
He'd worked on airborne radar
他曾经从事机载雷达的工作
that mapped bombers' targets on the ground.
为轰炸机绘制地面目标
But his real ambition was to build
但是他真正的雄心在于建造
something capable of mapping the heavens.
某种能描绘天国的东西
The giant dish at Jodrell Bank was Bernard Lovell's baby.
卓瑞尔河岸的巨型碟盘就是伯纳德·洛弗尔的杰作
It was designed to be the world's largest fully manoeuvrable
在设计它的时候，它是世界上最大的全机动的
radio telescope, capable of scouring the entire sky
射电望远镜，能够搜索整个天空
and picking up the longest-wavelength radio signals
能够检测到来自太空最深处的
coming from the deepest recesses of space.
最长波长的辐射信号
The Lovell Telescope has a collecting area
洛弗尔望远镜的接收面积
of 4,560 square metres,
为4560平方米，
made up of more than 2,400 galvanised steel plates.
用了超过2400块的镀锌钢板
In the original designs, this bowl of the telescope
在原来的设计中，望远镜的这个大碗
wasn't meant to be solid like this.
并不像这样固化
The plan was for it to be built of much lighter wire mesh.
原来的规划是用轻得多的金属丝网
The dish was redesigned
后来人们重新设计了这个盘子
because astronomers had discovered a new way of seeing in the dark,
因为天文学家们发现了一种看透黑暗的新方法
something that might ultimately allow them
这种方法可能最终能让他们
to map the universe's dark ages.
绘制宇宙的黑暗时代
Hydrogen permeates every galaxy.
氢原子弥漫着每一个星系
It was produced in the big bang
它是在大爆炸中产生的
and is the basic constituent of all normal matter, including us.
是所有常规物质,包括我们身体的基本成分.
And like most normal matter,
就像所有常规物质一样
it wasn't thought to give off any light.
氢原子只会发出特定的光
But then astronomers discovered something remarkable.
但是后来天文学家发现了某种不同寻常的现象
As it floats around in space,
当氢原子在太空漂浮的时候
neutral hydrogen gas is constantly producing radio waves
中性的氢原子气体总是持续产生无线电波
and, crucially, those waves are always the same wavelength - 21cm.
而且最关键的是，这些波的波长总是一样的 - 21厘米
And this meant that hydrogen could be used to map
这就意味着对于充满了氢原子的星系
the galaxies that it fills.
氢原子能够将它们描绘出来
By detecting the 21cm signal, the Lovell Telescope helped reveal
通过探测21厘米信号，洛弗尔望远镜帮助揭示了
the spiral structure of the Milky Way
银河系的螺旋结构
and produced detailed maps of distant galaxies.
并绘制了远距离星系的细节图像
But galaxies aren't the only place in the cosmos you find hydrogen gas.
但是星系并不是宇宙中含有氢气的唯一地方
During the dark ages of the universe,
在宇宙的黑暗时代
there were no galaxies, but there was plenty of hydrogen.
没有星系，却又足量的氢气
So by detecting the 21cm signal from these primordial gas clouds,
所以，通过探测这些原生气体云发出的21厘米信号
you could see the universe in its infancy
你就能看到婴儿期的宇宙
and peer into the dark ages themselves.
从而窥视到黑暗时代本身
And by doing so, we'll be able to watch dark matter
通过这种方式，我们将能够看到暗物质
pull the cosmos together...
把宇宙拉在一起...
..and light up the heavens.
..并点亮天国
It was during the dark ages that the hydrogen gas created
就是在黑暗时代，在大爆炸中产生的氢气
in the big bang was compressed into stars and moulded into galaxies.
被压缩成恒星，再构成星系
It was in this era that the cosmos as we know it was born,
就是在这个年代，我们所知道的宇宙诞生了
sculpted by the gravitational pull of dark matter.
并被暗物质的引力所雕塑
But the machine scientists are building to map the dark ages
科学家们正在建造新设备来绘制黑暗时代
will see far more.
它将比目前看到的多很多
With an effective collecting area of more than 200 times that
它的有效接收面积比洛弗尔望远镜
of the Lovell Telescope, the square kilometre array
大200倍，平方千米阵列
will be capable of mapping a billion galaxies,
将能够描绘十亿个星系
tracking the expansion and evolution of the entire universe
跟踪整个宇宙的膨胀和演化
more accurately than ever before.
并且比以前更精确
And the hope is, that by doing so,
我们期望，通过这种方法
it will provide clues to the nature of dark energy
它能够提供一些关于暗能量性质的线索
and the universe's ultimate fate.
以及宇宙终极命运的线索
Using hydrogen to map the cosmos might just represent the final
用氢原子描绘宇宙可能只代表
chapter of humankind's exploration of the universe using light,
人类用光探索宇宙的最后篇章
a journey that began in earnest some 400 years ago.
这个探索的旅程开始于大约400年前
In December 1609, Galileo Galilei began making observations
在1609年十二月，伽利略·伽利莱开始
of the night sky.
观察黑夜的天空
Before then, what was thought to be out there was essentially
在那之前，外太空存在什么
a matter of faith.
只是一个信仰问题
The universe at large lay unseen and unseeable.
整个宇宙，看不见的和不能看见的，就在那里
But now, for the first time,
但是现在，第一次
the nature of the heavens was something knowable -
天国的本性成为可知的东西
you simply had to look up and see it.
你只需要抬头仰望就行
The light captured in Galileo's simple telescope
进入到伽利略简陋的望远镜中的光线
began a chain of discoveries that would reveal
开启了一系列的发现，揭示了
the true nature of the cosmos.
宇宙的真实本性
We've seen galaxies
我们已经看到的星系
billions of light years' distance from the Earth.
远离地球数十亿光年
And as we've come to understand light's properties,
当我们理解了光的属性
we've discovered the stuff of which stars are made...
我们又发现了组成恒星的物质...
..and glimpsed the beginning of the universe itself.
..并瞥见了宇宙自己的起点
But the realisation that most normal matter can't be seen
但是人们认识到，许多常规物质我们看不到
and the discovery of dark matter and dark energy
还有暗物质和暗能量的发现
mean that more than 99% of the universe lies hidden in the shadows.
意味着宇宙的99%都隐藏于阴影之中
And as dark energy pushes the galaxies ever further apart,
随着暗能量把星系分离得更远
what few lights there are will begin to go out.
那里少量的光源将开始离我们远去
As the universe expands ever faster,
随着宇宙更快地膨胀
one by one the galaxies will disappear from view.
一个一个的星系将从我们的视野消失
All that will remain visible will be the stars in our own galaxy.
仍然能够看见的将只有我们自己星系中的恒星
It would be almost as if we'd never invented the telescope at all.
那就像我们从来没有发明过望远镜的时候一样
For the vast majority of the universe's life,
对于绝大多数宇宙中的生命来说
there'll be no way of discovering all the things we have about it.
他们将无法做出和我们一样的关于宇宙的发现
So I don't feel disheartened that so much of the cosmos
所以，尽管宇宙中如此多的东西隐藏于阴影之中
is hidden in the shadows.
但我不会感到沮丧
The real miracle is
真实的奇迹就是
that when we first looked out into the depths of space
当我们第一次向太空深处望去时
there was any light to see at all.
居然还能看到有光
Whether you want to step into the light
无论你想走进光明
or explore the mysteries of the dark,
还是想探索黑暗的神秘
let the Open University inspire you.
让开放大学来激励你
Go to...
请到
..and follow links to The Open University.
..顺着这个链接到开放大学
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd
英文字幕由红蜜蜂媒体有限公司提供
天马字幕组出品中文字幕
http://growupsoft.blog.163.com
翻译：旧语新思 马成长  校对：旧语新思 马成长
请保留翻译人员相关信息，勿作商业之用
华中农业大学《欣赏物理学》专用字幕
后期制作：旧语新思 马成长